Guide to the B. F. Dowell Papers 1850-1896
Oregon Historical Society, Research Library
B. F. Dowell papers
1850-1896
Oregon Historical Society, Davies Family Research Library Research Library 1200 SW Park Avenue Portland, Oregon 97205 Phone: 503-306-5240 Fax: 503-219-2040 E-mail: libreference@ohs.org
Mss 209
Dowell, Benjamin Franklin
.25 cubic feet (1 document case)
The collection contains a description of Dowell's trip from the eastern U.S. to Sacramento during the California gold rush, two scrapbooks of newspaper clippings, several pieces of correspondence to and from Dowell, a satiric poem by P.H. Bartlett and a printed flyer concerning an 1873 court case.
Biography of Benjamin Franklin Dowell:
Benjamin Franklin Dowell was born in Albemarle County, Virginia, in 1821. He received his law degree from the University of Virginia in 1847. He practiced law briefly in Tennessee before heading to the California gold fields in 1850. After a few months he moved north to Oregon, becoming a packer and trader in Jacksonville in 1852. In 1857 he returned to the practice of law, opening an office in Jacksonville. He married Anna Campbell in 1861. They had three children: Fannie, Annie, and Benjamin Franklin Jr. In 1885 they moved to Portland, and B.F. began to divide his time between Portland and Washington, D.C., where he prosecuted Indian war claims before Congress. Also in 1885 he purchased the Oregon Sentinel newspaper, which he published until his death in 1897.
The collection contains a description of Dowell's trip from the eastern U.S. to Sacramento during the California gold rush, two scrapbooks of newspaper clippings, several pieces of correspondence to and from Dowell, a satiric poem by P.H. Bartlett and a printed flyer concerning an 1873 court case.
The collection is arranged in one series.
The collection is open to the public.
Journal described in Overland Passages: a guide to overland documents in the Oregon Historical Society, entry 61, and Platte River road narratives, entry 776.
Origin of the collection is unknown.
The collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings:
Dowell, B. F. (Benjamin Franklin)
Pioneers -- Oregon -- Jackson County.; Lawyers -- Oregon -- Jacksonville.
Oregon; Government and Politics; Pioneers; Diaries; Scrapbooks
Narratives (document genre); Poetry; Scrapbooks; Correspondence; Fliers (printed matter)
- Journal (letter), 1850 (Folder 1)
  Narrative of his trip from St. Louis, Missouri, to Sacramento, California.
- Album, 1857 (Folder 2)
  Satiric poem and letter by P.H. Bartlett, transcribed by John A. Miller.
- Scrapbook, 1858 (Folder 3)
  Clippings used in preparation for speeches.
- Scrapbook, 1976 (Folder 3)
  Clippings and notes.
- Correspondence, 1862-1896
  - B.F. Bonham, 1862 (Folder 4)
  - Jesse Applegate, 1864; 1865 (Folder 4)
  - J.W. Hillman, 1865 (Folder 4)
  - O. Jacobs, 1867 (Folder 4)
  - T., 1868 (Folder 4)
  - Wm. Neffman (?), 1868 (Folder 4)
  - John Kelly, 1869 (Folder 4)
  - J.A. Baker, 1879 (Folder 4)
  - B.H. Brewster, 1883 (Folder 4)
  - A. G. T'Vault, 1896 (Folder 4)
- Thomas J. O'Neal court case, 1873 (Folder 5)